John Russell Young Correspondence
John Russell Young Correspondence
1874-1905
Young, John Russell, 1841-1899.
0.25 linear ft.
Papers of the American journalist, diplomat, Librarian of Congress. Incoming personal correspondence addressed to Young and his wife, May. Notes of congratulations on his wedding, responses to invitations, and letters concerning Mrs. Young's efforts to collect and publish her husband's writings after his death.
149314
Biographical History
John Russell Young (1841-1899) was an American journalist, editor and foreign minister. Born in Tyrone County, Ireland, Young emigrated at early age with his family to Pennsylvania. He served as a U.S. Civil War correspondent and was one of the first to report on the Battle of Bull Run. In 1877, General Grant invited him on an international tour, which spawned his book Around the World with General Grant and also resulted in Young's appointment to the post of minister to China.
In addition to his international work, Young also worked as editor for the New York Tribune, the New York Herald, and was appointed Librarian of Congress in 1897 by President McKinley. He died in 1899.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Russell Young Correspondence consists of incoming letters sent during 1890-1905. A number of the letters were written after Mr. Young's death and are addressed to his wife, May. Subjects include congratulations upon Young's marriage, responses to social invitations, acknowledgements of the birth of the Youngs' son, and answers to social correspondence. Correspondents include Alvey Adee, Edward P. Alexander, Edward Bok, George Cortelyou, F. Marion Crawford, Augustin Daly, L. Clarke Davis, Henry George, Arthur P. Gorman, Frederick Grant, Elijah Halford, Henry Cabot Lodge, Clarence Mackay, Nelson Miles, William W. Phelps, Whitelaw Reid, Daniel Sickles, David Sickles, Charles Emory Smith, Sara Yorke Stevenson, and Herbert Beerbohm Tree.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically by correspondent name.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Adee, Alvey A. (Alvey Augustus), 1842-1924.; Alexander, Edward Porter, 1835-1910.; Bok, Edward William, 1863-1930.; Cortelyou, George B. (George Bruce), 1862-1940.; Crawford, F. Marion (Francis Marion), 1854-1909.; Daly, Augustin, 1838-1899.; Davis, L. Clarke (Lemuel Clarke), 1835-1904.; George, Henry, 1862-1916.; Gorman, Arthur P. (Arthur Pue), 1839-1906.; Grant, Frederick Dent, 1850-1912.; Halford, Elijah Walker, 1843-1938.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924.; Mackay, Clarence H. (Clarence Hungerford), 1874-1938.; Miles, Nelson Appleton, 1839-1925.; Phelps, William Walter, 1839-1894.; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912.; Sickles, Daniel Edgar, 1819-1914.; Sickles, David Banks, 1837-1918.; Smith, Charles Emory, 1842-1908.; Stevenson, Sara Yorke, 1847-1921.; Tree, Herbert Beerbohm, Sir, 1853-1917.; Young, John Russell, 1841-1899.; Young, May Dow Russell.; Authors, American.; Journalists -- United States.; Philadelphia (Pa.), Social life and customs.; Correspondence.; Authors.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Adee, Alvey Augustus, 22 Nov 1890; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Edward Porter, 22 Apr 1895; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Bok, Edward William, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Carpenter, Matthew Hale, to "Dear Merchant", 1 Aug 1874; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Cortelyou, George Bruce, 17 Feb 1902; 1 Oct 1902; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Crawford, F. Marion, 21 Dec 1897; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Daly, Augustin, 16 Dec 1891; 18 Jan 1899; 2 letters (Box 1)
  - Davis, L. Clarke, 5 June 1896; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - George, Henry, 28 Nov 1890; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Gorman, Arthur Pue, 22 Nov 1890; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Grant, Frederick Dent, undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Halford, Elijah Walker, 22 Nov 1890; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Jefferson, Sarah A., undated; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 31 Jan 1899; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - MacKay, Clarence Hungerford, 31 May 1905; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Miles, Nelson Appleton, 20 Aug 1903; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Phelps, William Walter, 21 Feb 1892; 1 note on calling card (Box 1)
  - Reid, Whitelaw, 1902; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Sickles, Daniel Edgar, 24 Nov 1890; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Sickles, David Banks, 23 Nov 1890; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Smith, Charles Emory, 30 Oct 1901; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Stevenson, Sara Yorke, 9 Apr 1896; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Tree, Herbert Beerbolm, 14 Mar 1895; 15 Mar 1895,; undated; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - Whitney, Henry H., 16 Dec 1898; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 23 Dec 1897; undated; 2 letters (Box 1)